Guide to the J. Walter Thompson Company. Domestic Advertisements, part 1, 1875-2001 and undated, bulk 1920s-1990s RL.00687
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company. Domestic advertisements, part 1
1875-2001 and undated, bulk 1920s-1990s
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company
RL.00687
360 Linear Feet
300,000 Items
Founded in 1864, the J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT) was one of the oldest and largest advertising agencies in the United States. It was headquartered in New York. In 2023 the agency was absorbed into marketing and communications firm VML. The Domestic Advertisements Collection consists of print advertisements created by U.S. offices of the J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT). The bulk of the collection dates from the 1920s and after, but a few examples are available from as early as 1875. Print advertisements appear in a variety of formats--magazine, newspaper, color, black-and-white, proofs, tearsheets, negative transfers, clippings, along with a limited number of sketches for outdoor advertising installations. Some of the advertisements feature work from notable artists, such as Norman Rockwell, and photographers like Edward Steichen, Irving Penn, and Baron De Meyer. In addition to the actual advertisements, the files dating from the 1910s to 1950s often contain insertion schedules that provide the dates and names of the magazines or newspapers in which a given advertisement appeared. In general, proofs for JWT's long-time clients have been saved more systematically than those for accounts that JWT did not hold for a long time. The collection does not include advertisements which have been transferred to microfilm (see the JWT Microfilm Collection). Also, advertisements created for clients that JWT lost prior to the 1940s are less likely to have been saved, although some were microfilmed and are still available in that form. For some JWT clients there are no print advertisements at all in this collection. Among the most extensive files of print advertisements are those for the following JWT clients: Champion Spark Plug, Chesebrough-Ponds, Eastman Kodak (Instamatic, Pocket Instamatic, and Disc cameras, Kodak film), Ford Motor Company (consumer and dealer advertisements), R.T. French, Irving Trust Bank, J. Walter Thompson Company (house advertisements), Kraft Foods (including Kraft cheeses, Miracle Whip, Philadelphia Cream Cheese, and Velveeta), Lever Brothers (Lifebuoy, Lux, Close Up, Mrs. Butterworth), Pan American World Airways (passenger jet travel, cargo transportation), Radio Corporation of America (RCA) (RCA Victor recordings, consumer goods, National Broadcasting Company), Reader's Digest, Scott Paper, Seven-Up, Standard Brands (Chase and Sandborn, Fleischmann, Royal, Tenderleaf tea), and Warner-Lambert (primarily Listerine, including advertisements produced by the Lambert and Feasley agency). Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History. The collection is continued by the J. Walter Thompson Company. Domestic advertisements, part 2.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Domestic Advertisements Collection was initially transferred to the Rubenstein Library from the J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT) in 1987 and has had additions each year since then.
Historical Note
Beginning in 1919 the New York Office of the J. Walter Thompson Company began to systematically retain the advertisements it had created. The Statistical and Information Department, renamed the Information and Records Department in the 1920s, arranged the advertisements in scrapbooks. Initially, most of the advertisements preserved were tear sheets, the actual advertisements clipped from newspapers and magazines. By the 1930s, however, the department retained the final printers' proofs for magazine advertisements. The scrapbooks therefore began to be called proof books.
In the 1950s the responsibility for creating proof books fell to individual account groups. In addition to the account group proof books, a file clerk under the supervision of the Traffic Department maintained proofs. When no longer of current use, the file clerk transferred the proofs to a storeroom or records center. Throughout these years, individuals who helped create campaigns or who managed an account sometimes would maintain personal proof books.
In 1977 the New York Office established a Creative Library. Its responsibilities included the preservation on microfilm of all print advertisements, which was done for most of the 1980s. Imprints are located in the JWT Microfilm Collection; the originals were apparently destroyed after microfilming. The Creative Library has made an effort to create files of work from all major U.S. offices, so work from Atlanta, Chicago, Detroit, Los Angeles, San Francisco, and Washington, D.C., is better represented in the collection from the late 1970s and after. Where known, the office that created the advertisements is noted in the container list. In addition, JWT subsidiaries such as Brouillard Communications or Lord Geller Federico and Einstein (LGFE) are noted where their work has been identified.
Collection Overview
The Domestic Advertisements Collection consists of print advertisements created by U.S. offices of the J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT). The bulk of the collection dates from the 1920s and after, but a few examples are available from as early as 1875. Print advertisements appear in a variety of formats--magazine, newspaper, color, black-and-white, proofs, tearsheets, negative transfers, clippings, along with a limited number of sketches for outdoor advertising installations. Some of the advertisements feature work from notable artists, such as Norman Rockwell, and photographers like Edward Steichen, Irving Penn, and Baron De Meyer. In addition to the actual advertisements, the files dating from the 1910s to 1950s often contain insertion schedules that provide the dates and names of the magazines or newspapers in which a given advertisement appeared. In general, proofs for JWT's long-time clients have been saved more systematically than those for accounts that JWT did not hold for a long time. The collection does not include advertisements which have been transferred to microfilm (see the JWT Microfilm Collection). Also, advertisements created for clients that JWT lost prior to the 1940s are less likely to have been saved, although some were microfilmed and are still available in that form. For some JWT clients there are no print advertisements at all in this collection. Among the most extensive files of print advertisements are those for the following JWT clients: Champion Spark Plug, Chesebrough-Ponds, Eastman Kodak (Instamatic, Pocket Instamatic, and Disc cameras, Kodak film), Ford Motor Company (consumer and dealer advertisements), R.T. French, Irving Trust Bank, J. Walter Thompson Company (house advertisements), Kraft Foods (including Kraft cheeses, Miracle Whip, Philadelphia Cream Cheese, and Velveeta), Lever Brothers (Lifebuoy, Lux, Close Up, Mrs. Butterworth), Pan American World Airways (passenger jet travel, cargo transportation), Radio Corporation of America (RCA) (RCA Victor recordings, consumer goods, National Broadcasting Company), Reader's Digest, Scott Paper, Seven-Up, Standard Brands (Chase and Sandborn, Fleischmann, Royal, Tenderleaf tea), and Warner-Lambert (primarily Listerine, including advertisements produced by the Lambert and Feasley agency).
The Collection is organized into three series--Main Files, Small Files, and Oversize Materials--that reflect both the size of the holdings for each client as well as the physical location of the advertisements. Within each series, clients are arranged alphabetically and then the advertisements are arranged chronologically. The Main File Series includes clients for which at least one box have been preserved. A separate Small Files Series is maintained for clients for which less than one box of advertisements, and often much less, has survived. The Oversize Materials Series includes many of the clients found in both the Main and Small Files Series.
The collection is continued by the J. Walter Thompson Company. Domestic advertisements, part 2.
Collection Overview
Chesebrough Ponds, 1875-1968. Proofs from the 1920s to 1950s feature testimonial advertising for Pond's Cold Cream. Noted socialites endorsing the product were photographed by well known photographers, including Edward J. Steichen and Baron DeMeyer.
Eastman Kodak Company, 1930-present. Organized into two categories--Consumer and Trade advertisements--that correspond to Kodak's two major marketing areas. Consumer advertisements feature photographs by well known photographers, famous slogans and trademarks, and depict the American family over several decades in settings where the cameras are used. Introductions of new camera models are well represented, including the Instamatic in 1963, the Pocket Instamatic in 1972, the Instant camera in 1975, and the Disc camera in 1982. At different times JWT handled both film and cameras (still and/or movie) or just Kodak films. Trade advertisements include campaigns for medical and industrial films, Kodel fibers, and Eastman Chemical, as well as advertisements aimed at Kodak dealers. Additional Kodak advertising may be found in the Wayne P. Ellis Collection of Kodakiana.
Ford Motor Company, 1945-present. Key campaigns include There's a Ford in Your Future (1945-1948), the Peanuts campaign (1960-1962) and the launch of the Mustang (1964). In addition to print advertisements showing the introduction of new models, photostats of outdoor billboards in the 1940s and early 1950s are included. Truck and dealer advertising can also be found. A separate collection, the JWT Detroit Office's Ford Collateral Literature, houses showroom brochures, and diverse sales materials in many formats.
Irving Trust, 1918-1986. Fine line drawings, often of New York City locales, appear in 1920s newspaper advertisements.
J. Walter Thompson Co., 1917-present. These house advertisements are an important source of information about the Company's operations and philosophy.
Kraft Foods Corporation, 1922-present. Advertisements for products including Miracle Whip, Velveeta, Philadelphia Cream Cheese, other cheeses, salad dressings, etc. and a number of lesser-known early products are present. Includes many advertisements with recipes and many trade advertisements directed at grocers.
Lever Brothers, 1900-present. The earliest advertisements are for Lifebuoy Soap. J. Walter Thompson Co. introduced Lux Flakes in 1915 and Lux Toilet Soap in 1925. The early Lux Flakes advertisements employed the talents of fine illustrators. Comic style advertising appeared in the 1930s (Peggy Lux and others). The Lux Toilet Soap campaigns began featuring movie and stage star testimonials in 1927. One noteworthy campaign dates from 1953-1954 when Irving Penn photographed some of Hollywood's most famous stars. The Lever Brothers advertisements for both Lux products also include photographs of car cards (subway and bus posters) from the 1920s. Other Lever products represented in the collection include Stripe and Close Up toothpastes, Mrs. Butterworth syrup, and Lever 2000 bath soap.
Massachusetts Mutual Insurance Company, 1951-1967. Although few in number, many of the advertisements contain Norman Rockwell illustrations. The original art work has been retained by the client.
Pan American World Airways, 1942-1974. Contains advertisements prepared for both U.S. and international consumers and includes the introduction of jet passenger travel. Cargo advertising also can be found.
RCA (Radio Corporation of America), 1943-1976. In addition to consumer products, advertisements for the National Broadcasting Company (NBC) programs can be found in this group.
Reader's Digest, 1945-present. Many of the advertisements since the 1960s highlight articles appearing in the current month's issue. Examples of corporate advertising for international editions of Reader's Digest are also present.
Scott Paper Co., 1927-1983. Numerous product introductions are represented.
Seven-Up, 1944-1978. Shows the changes in positioning this beverage from a family drink to Wet 'n' Wild to the Un-Cola.
Standard Brands, 1925-1984. Advertisements cover a range of products, including Fleischmann's Yeast, Chase and Sanborn, Tenderleaf Tea, and Royal Pudding and Gelatin.
Warner-Lambert, 1915-1997. Advertisements consist primarily of proofs and tearsheets. There are no advertisements present for the years 1945-1947 or 1949. The vast majority of the advertisements are for Listerine Antiseptic, with other products represented beginning in the late 1960s. Listerine was manufactured by the Lambert Pharmacal Company beginning around 1915. William Warner acquired the company in 1955, merged it into his own pharmaceutical business and changed the name to the Warner-Lambert Co.
Warner-Lambert is the only client file in this collection that includes the work of an agency other than JWT. Until 1962, Listerine advertising was handled by the Lambert and Feasley agency in New York, the house agency for the Lambert Pharmacal Co. (St. Louis) up to 1955, and for its successor the Warner-Lambert Co. (Morris Plains, N.J.), from 1955-1962. When JWT obtained the Listerine account in October 1962, the back files of Listerine advertisements were transferred to JWT.
Related Archival Materials note
Related materials within the J. Walter Thompson Company Archives:
World War II Advertising Collection.
Microfilm Collection--contains 104 reels of advertisements dating from 1906 to 1960, and includes West Coast offices from 1916 to 1928 and international offices from 1927 to 1933.
Newsletter Collection, especially those dating from 1946 and after.
Publications: J.Walter Thompson Advertising, Thompson Red Book, and Thompson Blue Books, 1887-1912.
Account Files Collection.
Client Lists.
Competitive Advertisements Collection. Although these primarily contain advertisments of non-JWT clients (i.e. competitor's advertising), this collection sometimes contains JWT advertisements. May also include advertisements of various JWT clients before or after they worked with JWT.
International Advertisements Collection. Especially strong in advertisements from JWT offices in Montreal (1940-1980) and Frankfurt, Germany (1950s-1980s) and small numbers of advertisements from many other JWT offices worldwide.
Mounted Advertisements Collection.
Review Board Records.
Atlanta Office. United States Marine Corps Account Records.
Chicago Office. Account Files.
Chicago Office. Hyatt Hotels Corp. Account Files.
Chicago Office. Quaker Oats Account Files.
Detroit Office. Ford Collateral Literature.
Detroit Office. Ford Dealer Association Records.
Frankfurt Office. Advertisements.
New York Office. Best of the Month Slides.
J. Walter Thompson Company. Domestic advertisements, part 2
Other related, non-JWT collections:
Wayne P. Ellis Collection of Kodiakiana (for Kodak-related materials).
Liggett and Myers Collection.
Lightner Collection of Antique Advertisements (for early automobile advertisements).
Gary P. and Sandra G. Baden Collection of Print Advertisements.
Outdoor Advertising Association of America Slide Library (image descriptions for this vast collection are accessible through the ROAD database).
War Effort Mobilization Campaigns Poster Collection.
Sketches; Advertising -- United States -- History; Advertising -- Transportation; Clippings (information artifacts); Advertising; Proofs (printed matter); Advertisements; Advertising agencies -- History; Advertising -- Automobiles -- United States; Advertising photography -- United States; Advertising -- Food -- United States; Advertising -- Soap; Advertising, Outdoor -- United States; Reader's Digest Association; Warner-Lambert Company; Steichen, Edward, 1879-1973; Standard Brands Incorporated; Seven-Up Company; Scott Paper Company; Rockwell, Norman, 1894-1978; Radio Corporation of America; R.T. French Company; Penn, Irving; Pan American World Airways, Inc.; Lever Brothers Company; Kraft Foods Company; Lambert and Feasley (Company); J. Walter Thompson Company; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; J. Walter Thompson Company. New York Office; J. Walter Thompson Company. Detroit Office; J. Walter Thompson Company. Frankfurt Office; J. Walter Thompson Company. Atlanta Office; J. Walter Thompson Company. Chicago Office; Ford Motor Company; Irving Trust Company; De Meyer, Adolf, Baron, 1868-1949; Eastman Kodak Company; Champion Spark Plug (Company); Chesebrough-Pond's.
- Main Files Series, 1875-2001 and undated
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes clients for which at least one box (usually at least 100 advertisements) have been preserved. A few files contain photocopies or prints made from microfilm, a fact which is noted in the list. Parenthetical identification of the client or product or the JWT office or division responsible for the ad has been added in some cases. The files are arranged alphabetically by client (not product), insofar as it has been possible to determine the client name accurately and as it was known during the relationship with JWT (hence, Lever Brothers in lieu of Unilever). The files are then arranged chronologically within client groupings.
  The main clients in this series include Chesebrough Ponds, Eastman Kodak Company, Ford Motor Company, Irving Trust Bank, J. Walter Thompson Co., Kraft Foods Corporation, Lever Brothers, Massachusetts Mutual Insurance Company, Pan-American Airlines, RCA (Radio Corporation of America), Reader's Digest, Scott Paper Co., Seven-Up, Standard Brands, and Warner-Lambert. The clients in this series are NOT represented in the Small Files Series but MAY have advertisements in the Oversize Series.
  - Advertising Council (Ad Council) and other public service clients, 1947-1995
    - Advertising Council, 1949-1951, 1983 (Box AD1)
      Advertisements for Ad Council as the client.
      [See also Oversize Folder 1.]
    - American Cancer Society, 1952 (Box AD1)
    - American Foundation for AIDS Research (Climb for the Cure), 1992 (Box AD1)
    - American Red Cross, 1957, 1964, 1967, 1970, 1977-1978, 1982-1986, 1988-1991, 5 folders (Box AD1)
      [See also Oversize Folder 4.]
    - Better Schools, 1949-1954 (Box AD2)
    - Bob Hope Heart Research Institute, 1985 (Box AD2)
    - BOM (Boysville)--Detroit, ca. 1996 (Box AD2)
    - Boy Scouts of America, 1972-1973, 1981-1982 (Chicago), 1984 (Boy Scouts of Greater New York) (Box AD2)
      [See also Oversize Folder 6.]
    - California Arts Council (Sacramento), 1989 (Box AD2)
    - Catholic Charities Dept. of Foster Family Services (Chicago), 1972, 1988 (Box AD2)
    - Children's Literacy Initiative (Mrs. Bush's Storytime), ca. 1990 (Box AD2)
    - Children's Memorial Hospital (Chicago), 1995 (Box AD2)
    - Church World Service, 1948 (Box AD2)
    - Civil Defense, 1954 (Box AD2)
    - Coalition on Donation (organ donation), ca. 1990s (Box AD2)
    - Committee for Handgun Control (Ban the Bullets)--Chicago, 1975 (Box AD2)
    - COPSA Institute for Alzheimers' Disease, ca. 1990s (Box AD2)
    - Crusade For Freedom (Radio Free Europe/Free Europe Press), 1956-1957 (Box AD2)
    - Cystic Fibrosis, 1982 (Box AD2)
      [See also Oversize Box OV3.]
    - Department of Housing and Urban Development (HUD)--Atlanta, Philadelphia, Tampa, 1985, 1992-1994 (Box AD2)
    - Executive Service Corp. of Chicago, 1987 (Box AD2)
    - Hospice Foundation of Southeastern Michigan, 1989 (Box AD3)
    - Literary Council of Chicago, 1985 (Box AD3)
    - March of Dimes, ca. 1990 (Box AD3)
    - Museum of Contemporary Art (Chicago), 1981 (Box AD3)
    - National Bible Week, 1991 (Box AD3)
    - NATO, 1957, 1964, 1984 (Box AD3)
      [See also Oversize Folder 36.]
    - New England Earth Day (Brouillard), 1990 (Box AD3)
    - New York Cares (coat drive), 1996 (Box AD3)
    - Nurse recruitment, 1947-1951 (Box AD3)
    - Partnership for a Drug-Free America, 1989-1990s (Box AD3)
    - President's Council on Youth Opportunity (Give a Damn), 1968 (Box AD3)
    - Providence--St. Mel High School (Chicago), 1982-1983 (Box AD3)
    - Red Nose Day USA for Sudden Infant Death Syndrome (SIDS), ca. 1990s (Box AD3)
    - Religion in American Life (RIAL), 1949-1970, 2 folders (Box AD3)
    - Salvation Army, 1962, 1970, 1972-1978, 1980-1986, 1988-1995 (Box AD4)
    - San Francisco AIDS Foundation, 1996 (Box AD4)
    - Save the Cable Cars (San Francisco), 1983 (Box AD4)
    - Statue of Liberty--Ellis Island Foundation, 1986 (Box AD4)
    - United America (tolerance campaign), ca. 1950s (Box AD4)
    - United Cerebral Palsy, 1972, 1977-1978, 1980, ca. 1984, 1987 (Box AD4)
    - United Foundations (Detroit), 1966-1967, 1970, 1972-1973 (Box AD4)
    - United Service Organizations (USO), 1961 (Box AD4)
    - United Way, ca. 1990s (Box AD4)
    - U.S. Food and Drug Administration (product tampering), 1987 (Box AD4)
    - Vehicle Emmissions Check Committee (U.S. Jaycees), 1974 (Box AD4)
    - U.S. Savings Bonds, 1948-1952, 1954, 1956-1957, and undated, 9 folders (Box AD5)
  - Alberto-Culver, 1963-1970
    - 1963-1970 (Box AC1)
  - Allegheny Airlines: see US Air (Box AC1)
  - Allied Signal (formerly Garrett), 1969-1989
    [See also Oversize Box OV1.]
    - 1969, 1974, 1978-1984, 1986-1989 (Box AS1)
  - Aluminum Limited/ALCAN, 1953-1976
    - 1953-1959 (Box AL1)
    - 1960-1969, 1973-1976 (Box AL2)
  - American Cancer Society: see Advertising Council (Box AL2)
  - American Gas Association, 1966-1997
    - 1966-1972, 1974-1980 (Box AG1)
    - 1980-1984, 1986-1997 (Box AG2)
  - American Red Cross: see Advertising Council (Box AG2)
  - American Weekly, 1941-1950
    - 1941-1943 (Box AW1)
    - 1941-1950,Insertion schedules (Box AW1)
    - 1944-1946 (Box AW2)
    - 1947-1950 (Box AW3)
  - Ameritech (American Information Technologies), 1983-1988
    [See also Oversize Box OV2.]
    - 1983-1985 (Box AI1)
    - 1986-1988 (Box AI2)
  - Andrew Jergens Co., 1915-1935
    - 1915-1935 (Box AJ1)
  - Atlantic Mutual Companies ( Brouillard), 1986-1997
    - 1986-1997 (insurance) (Box AM1)
  - Australian Meat and Livestock Corp. ( Brouillard), 1988-1997
    - 1988-1997 (Box AU1)
  - Bally Manufacturing Corporation, 1974-1991
    Formerly Health and Tennis Corp. of America; includes Vic Tanny, Richard Simmons, Chicago Health and Raquetball.
    [See also Oversize Box 18, Oversize Folder 21.]
    - 1974-1980 (Box BM1)
    - 1981-1991 (Box BM2)
  - Bausch and Lomb, 1970-1981
    [See also Oversize Folder 5.]
    - 1970-1971 (Box BL1)
    - 1972-1981 (Box BL2)
  - Beatrice Foods, 1984-1987
    - 1984-1987 (Box BF1)
  - Bell Atlantic, 1988-1991
    - 1988-1991 (Box BA1)
  - Benetton, 1984-1992
    - 1984-1988 (Box BE1)
    - 1988-1991 (Box BE2)
    - 1992 (Box BE3)
  - Better Schools: see Advertising Council (Box BE3)
  - Blue Cross/Blue Shield, 1940-1991
    - 1940-1946 (Box BC1)
    - 1947-1953 (Box BC2)
    - 1954-1956 (Box BC3)
    - 1957-1963 (Box BC4)
    - 1964-1971 (Box BC5)
    - 1972-1981 (Box BC6)
    - 1982-1984, 1986-1991 (Box BC7)
  - Booth Publishing, 1973-1984
    - 1973-1984 (Box BP1)
  - Brillo Manufacturing, 1943-1967
    - 1943-1949 (Box BR1)
    - 1950-1967 (Box BR2)
  - Burger King, 1975-1987
    [See also Oversize Box OV2; Oversize Folder 7.]
    - 1975-1987 (Box BK1)
  - Burlington Industries, 1951-1958, 1980-1982
    - 1951-1958, 1980-1982 (Box BI1)
  - Burroughs, 1954-1969
    - 1954, 1961-1966, 1968-1969 (Box BU1)
  - Campbell Taggart Associated Bakeries (Chicago), 1970-1973
    - 1970-1973 (Box CA1)
  - Champion Spark Plug, 1955-1986
    [See also Oversize Folder 10.]
    - 1955-1961 (Box CS1)
    - 1962-1963 (Box CS2)
    - 1964-1965 (Box CS3)
    - 1966-1969 (Box CS4)
    - 1970-1971 (Box CS5)
    - 1972-1973 (Box CS6)
    - 1974-1976 (Box CS7)